BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH

NAME: Gabry, Jonah S.

eRA COMMONS USER NAME: NA

POSITION TITLE: Staff Associate (research in Statistics)

EDUCATION/TRAINING

INSTITUTION AND LOCATION	DEGREE	Completion Date	FIELD OF STUDY
Bowdoin College (Brunswick, ME)	B.A.	05/2007	History, Spanish, Music
University of Pennsylvania (Philadelphia, PA)	PostBac	05/2013	Mathematics and Statistics
Columbia University (New York, NY)	M.A.	05/2015	Quantitative Methods in the Social Sciences

A. Personal Statement

I am a staff research associate at Columbia University, having just completed my master program in Quantitative Methods in the Social Sciences at Columbia University. I will be a contributing 50% effort to this project to make complex hierarchical modeling more accessible to data scientist.

A large part of my work so far focused on creating and improving methods and tools for applied statisticians. The software packages I develop with the principal investigators of this project and their collaborators (rstan, rstanarm and shiynstan, described in greater detail in Section C) are intended to make the process of Bayesian data analysis more accessible for researchers and to disseminate the advanced ultra-fast MCMC algorithms implemented in Stan and developed by the team around Professor Andrew Gelman. We are also working on complimentary software tools focusing on multilevel regression and post-stratification of survey data. In addition to my work on software for Bayesian data analysis, I am also responsible for survey weights and imputation of missing data for the New York City Longitudinal Survey of Wellbeing, a study carried out by the Columbia Population Research Center.

My role in this project will be Jonah to contribute to the development of the existing and the writing of novel functions, routines and algorithms for **rstanarm**. I will implement new graphical tools and interfaces, novel analytical tools for **shinystan** in close collaboration with Michael Betancourt.

I look forward to applying my experience in statistical software development and knowledge of hierarchical (multilevel) modeling to this exciting multi-disciplinary collaboration to make advanced Bayesian multilevel modeling more accessible to clinical data scientists.

B. Positions and Honors

Positions and Employment

2008-2010	Directory of Customer Accounts, Midwest European Publications, Cambridge, MA & Skokie IL
2010-2013	Freelance translator and computer programmer, Buenos Aires, Argentina & Philadelphia, PA
2013-2014	Graduate research assistant, Columbia University, New York, NY
	Earth Institute (Millennium Villages Project)
2014-2015	Graduate research assistant, Columbia University, New York, NY
	Political Science Department
2015-present	Researcher in Statistics (Staff Associate level), Columbia University, New York, NY

Other Experience

2015-Present Stan Core Development Team

Honors and Awards

Quantitative Methods in the Social Sciences Scholarship, Columbia University, 2013 Honors for thesis on Spanish-English translation, Bowdoin College, 2007 Philip C. Bradley Prize, Bowdoin College, 2007 Latin American Studies Prize, Bowdoin College, 2007 Phi Beta Kappa & Cum Laude, Bowdoin College, 2007 Bowdoin College Research Grant, 2006

C. Contribution to Science

My contribution to science has been in authoring or contributing to user centered software package for the open source statistical environment R to facilitate advanced Bayesian hierarchical modeling as a member of Stan Core Development Team. The **rstanarm** and **shinystan** packages stands out by their integration and by breaking down the significant barriers that hitherto existed for data scientist to utilize the power of the cutting edge Hamiltonian Monte Carlo algorithms for fitting complex hierarchical models.

Co-authored software packages:

loo Efficient approximate leave-one-out cross-validation (LOO) using Pareto smoothed importance sampling (PSIS), a new procedure for regularizing importance weights. As a byproduct of the calculations, we also obtain approximate standard errors for estimated predictive errors, and for the comparison of predictive errors between models. https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/loo/index.html

rstan User-facing R functions are provided by this package to parse, compile, test, estimate, and analyze Stan models by accessing the header-only Stan library provided by the 'StanHeaders' package. The Stan project develops a probabilistic programming language that implements full Bayesian statistical inference via Markov Chain Monte Carlo, rough Bayesian inference via variational approximation, and (optionally penalized) maximum likelihood estimation via optimization. In all three cases, automatic differentiation is used to quickly and accurately evaluate gradients without burdening the user with the need to derive the partial derivatives. https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/rstan/index.html

rstanarm Estimates pre-compiled regression models using the 'rstan' package, which provides the R interface to the Stan C++ library for Bayesian estimation. Users specify models via the customary R syntax with a formula and data.frame plus some additional arguments for priors. https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/rstanarm/index.html

shinystan A graphical user interface for interactive Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) diagnostics and plots and tables helpful for analyzing a posterior sample. The interface is powered by RStudio's Shiny web application framework and works with the output of MCMC programs written in any programming language (and has extended functionality for Stan models fit using the rstan package and the No-U-Turn sampler). https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/shinystan/index.html

Co-authored papers and conference abstracts/presentations:

Vehtari, A., Gelman, A., Gabry, J. (2016). *Practical Bayesian model evaluation using leave-one-out cross-validation and WAIC*. Preprint available on arXiv (http://arxiv.org/abs/1507.04544)

Gabry J, Andreae MH, Yuanjun Gao, Dongying Song. *Interactive graphical analysis, exploration and posterior predictive checking of multi-level hierarchical Bayesian models*. Oral Presentation at the Annual Meeting of the International Society of Clinical Biostatistics, Utrecht, NL, 2015.

Andreae MH, White R, Gabry J, Hall C. *Utilization of antiemetic medication as a marker of health care disparities in anesthesia*. Abstract at the Translational Science Conference, Washington, 2015.

D. Research Support

Ongoing research support

NSF Grant: SES-1424962

PI: Justin Phillips

Award Period: 9/15/14 – 8/31/17

This research focuses on using multilevel regression and post-stratification (MRP) to measure and study dynamic public opinion. My primary responsibilities are to develop MRP methods that extend to time series data and implement software tools using R and Stan to make MRP more accessible to social science researchers working with survey data and facilitate future research on the topic.

Robin Hood Foundation CU11-1145

PI: Irv Garfinkel

Award Period: 11/1/14-4/30/16

The New York City Longitudinal Survey of Wellbeing is designed to track the dynamics of poverty, hardship, and wellbeing over time among the population of 18+ residents of New York City. My responsibilities include producing imputations of missing data and constructing survey weights to adjust for known differences between sample and population as well as survey non-response.